Mary Ritter Beard papers SSC.MS.00013
Sophia Smith Collection
Mary Ritter Beard papers
1915 - 1958
Sophia Smith Collection
Beard, Mary Ritter, 1876-1958
SSC.MS.00013
2 boxes (2.25 linear feet)
Historian, archivist, and women's rights activist. The Mary Ritter Beard papers primarily document the organization and dissolution of the World Center for Women's Archives, which Beard founded, as well as the founding of both the Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College and the Schlesinger Library at Radcliffe College, both women's history archives. Materials include correspondence, writings, photographs, and books. Correspondents include Dorothy Brush; Ethel Weed; prominent Japanese activist and Diet member, Shizue Kato; Sophia Smith Collection founder, Margaret Grierson; and Grierson's companion, Marine Leland.
Biographical / Historical
Mary Ritter Beard was born in Indianapolis on 5 August 1876, the third of six children and the elder of two daughters of Narcissa (Lockwood) and Eli Foster Ritter. At sixteen she left home to attend De Pauw University in Asbury, Indiana, where she studied political science, languages, and literature. She graduated in 1897 and taught high school German until 1900 when she married Charles Austin Beard, whom she had met at De Pauw. Mary Beard accompanied her husband to Oxford, and both were active politically as well as academically. Charles helped organize Ruskin Hall, the "free university" aimed at workingmen, and Mary became involved with the British women's suffrage movement. They returned to New York in 1902. Their daughter Miriam was born in 1903. The following year the Beards enrolled at Columbia University, but Mary quit soon after to take care of their child and volunteer for progressive causes.
Following the birth of her son William in 1907, Mary Beard became an organizer for the National Women's Trade Union League. From 1910 to 1912 she edited the suffragist periodical The Woman Voter, and after that worked with the Wage Earner's League. She was a member of the militant faction of the suffrage movement led by Alice Paul from 1913 to 1919, and she worked on several progressive causes. During this period, Charles taught at Columbia University, but he resigned in 1917 in protest of the firing of anti-war faculty. Charles helped establish the New School for Social Research and both Beards helped found the Workers Education Bureau, but by the early 1920, the Beards generally worked outside of academic institutions.
Following her resignation from the National Woman's Party in 1917, Mary Beard devoted her skills and efforts to writing and lecturing, rather than public political activity. Her first book, Woman's Work in Municipalities (1915) and her second, A Short History of the American Labor Movement (1920), focused on social reform and the working class. With Charles, she co-authored The Rise of American Civilization (1927), a groundbreaking text that integrated political, economic, social, and cultural histories with a progressive vision of America's past and distinctive national character. The two collaborated on several books that would become some of the most enduringly significant American history texts, but by herself, Mary pioneered the field of women's history. She was appalled by the omission of women from the historical record, and she wrote about and promoted the recognition of women's achievements in the present day and the past, in the U.S. and internationally. She authored and edited Understanding Women (1931), America Through Women's Eyes (1933), A Changing Political Economy as It Affects Women (1934), and Women as Force in History (1946), among others.
Rather than concentrating on grievances and questions of the subjugation of women, Beard's work promoted women's contributions to the formation of society and brought to light a long-neglected past. To this end in the early 1930s, she collaborated with Hungarian pacifist feminist Rosika Schwimmer to organize the World Center for Women's Archives (WCWA). Beard quoted French historian Fustel de Coulanges for the motto of the WCWA: "No documents, no history," and she envisioned an archive of women's papers and organizational records that would provide a foundation for women's history as an academic field as well as serve as a public good. Beard and Schwimmer raised funds, founded a board of directors, and collected documents from their network of women activists. The WCWA was headquartered in New York but collected on an international level. It was a well-publicized effort, and though the collection specialized in material from the pacifist movement, Beard worked to realize a broader conception for a collection representing the range of women's activities. Factionalism among WCWA supporters, shaky financial support, and an increasingly militaristic atmosphere in the U.S. and abroad forced the dissolution of the WCWA in the early 1940s.
This development was very discouraging to Beard, but fortunately, the WCWA generated momentum for developing institutions of women's history. Beard worked closely with Smith College archivist Margaret Grierson to create the Sophia Smith Collection, one of the world's largest women's history manuscript collections, founded in 1942, and she worked with Harvard historians to create the eventual Schlesinger Library at Radcliffe. These two institutions received many of the WCWA documents, as did several smaller collections. Together, they carried on the WCWA mission, at least partly due to Beard's influence.
Neither of the Beards avoided controversy in their writings or public stands. Though both were well-respected historians, they increasingly drew criticism for their pacifist and progressive politics in the years surrounding World War II. Charles Beard died in 1948, and Mary Ritter Beard died on 14 August 1958. Both Beards have had enduring reputations as incisive historians, and they are recognized for their pioneering work in social history. Mary Beard especially has been celebrated for her work to promote women's history.
Nancy Cott has written about Mary Beard as an activist, historian, and pioneer in the field of women's history in several articles and books, and she edited a volume of Beard's correspondence, A Woman Making History: Mary Beard through Her Letters (1991). Ann Lane's Mary Ritter Beard: A Sourcebook (1977) was edited and re-released in 2000 as Making Women's History: the Essential Mary Beard. Barbara Turoff's biography, Mary Beard as Force in History, was published in 1979.
Scope and Contents
The Mary Ritter Beard Papers are a small but significant collection of Beard's correspondence, writings, and materials from the World Center for Women's Archives (WCWA). Beard destroyed most of her personal papers. Nonetheless, what remains provides fascinating insight into one of the most significant American intellectuals of the twentieth century. Margaret Storrs Grierson, Smith College Archivist, established the Sophia Smith Collection (SSC), one the largest repositories for primary sources in women's history, in consultation with Beard. The documents in this collection pertain primarily to the years surrounding the demise of the WCWA and the founding of the Sophia Smith Collection.
A small amount of biographical material includes photographs and clippings. The correspondence spans the mid-1940s to early 1950s. Letters exchanged between Beard, Dorothy [Dick] Brush, and Ethel Weed pertain to a proposed book on Japanese women's history. The project began as a collaboration between Brush and Beard. Beard ultimately authored Woman as Force in Japanese History (1953). Ethel Weed provided research assistance and served as a liaison between Beard and Shidzue Kato, a prominent Japanese activist and Diet member involved in the drafting of the Japanese Constitution following World War II.
Correspondence between Beard, Margaret Grierson, and Grierson's companion Marine Leland offers special insight into Beard's personal life. The correspondence details Beard's professional life in the 1940s and 1950s as well. She deposited the materials from the defunct WCWA at Smith, Radcliffe College (at what would become the Schlesinger Library), and elsewhere, and the correspondence documents Beard's efforts to continue the mission of the WCWA. Beard and Grierson collaborated to establish the Sophia Smith Collection and sought each other's advice in their efforts to preserve and promote women's history. There is a microfilmed copy of Beard's outgoing correspondence that includes correspondence in the Beard Papers and other collections of the Sophia Smith Collection. See the Appendix at the end of this finding aid for a list of correspondents.
The writings of Mary Beard include printed magazine articles and speeches. A typed and printed syllabus and bibliography prepared for the American Association of University Women analyzes the "Changing Political Economy as it Affects Women." There are also typescripts and research materials from various projects undertaken by Beard in the 1940s, including notes on women in American history and a study of the representation of women in the Enclyclopedia Britannica. A significant amount of material was generated from the Japanese women's history project. The collection contains third party correspondence concerning research and the manuscript, typescripts of sections of the project, and research materials, including clippings about Shidzue Kato [see also incoming correspondence from Ethel Weed for notes from an interview of Kato]. The Papers contain printed copies of several of Beard's books, including those coauthored with Charles Beard.
The last section of material concerns the World Center for Women's Archives. The materials in Beard Papers pertaining to the WCWA consist of correspondence, which includes letters to the general membership regarding the dissolution of the WCWA and letters between Mary Ritter Beard and donors to the archive; a file of general material; and a report from Dora Ettinger about women in Germany that was intended to become a WCWA document.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Writings
IV. World Center for Women's Archives
Appendix: The Letters of Mary R. Beard, 1934-1955
Microfilmed from the holdings of the Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College.
FROM THE MARY R. BEARD PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Dorothy Brush, 1946-1956
Mary R. Beard to Mrs. Chamberlin, 1940
Mary R. Beard to Margaret S. Grierson, 1941-1956
Mary R. Beard to Eva B. Hansl, 1947
Mary R. Beard to to Alice Lachmund, 1941-1950
Mary R. Beard to Marine Leland, 1947-1951
Mary R. Beard to Margaret Sanger, n.d.
Mary R. Beard to Ethel Weed, 1946-1952
FROM THE NANCY COX-McCORMACK CUSHMAN PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Nancy Cox-McCormack Cushman, 1940-1952
FROM THE EVA B. HANSL PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Eva B. Hansl, 1941
FROM THE FLORENCE ROSE PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Florence Rose, 1937-1939
FROM THE MARGARET SANGER PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Mary Compton, 1946
Mary R. Beard to Miss Nelson, 1951
Mary R. Beard to Margaret Sanger, 1951-1952
FROM THE JOSEPHINE SCHAIN PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Dr. Maffett, 1940
FROM THE MARGERY STEER PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Margery Steer, 1950-1955
FROM THE MARY VAN KLEECK PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Mary van Kleeck, 1935
FROM THE RUTH WOODSMALL PAPERS:
Mary R. Beard to Mrs. Blaisdell, 1934
Additional Formats
Portions of correspondence, including correspondence from other collections, are also available on microfilm; in Sophia Smith Collection and through interlibrary loan.
Related Material
The Mary Ritter Beard Papers at the Sophia Smith Collection are one of the three primary collections of Beard's papers. DePauw University and the Schlesinger Library also have collections.
For additional Beard material, including correspondence from Beard in other manuscript collections, see the Sophia Smith Collection card catalog and the Donor Files of the Sophia Smith Collection (stored in the Smith College Archives).
See also Revealing Women's Life Stories: Papers from the 50th Anniversary Celebration of the Sophia Smith Collection for article on Mary Beard by Nancy F. Cott.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Beard Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in the early 1940s after the dissolution of the World Center of Women's Archives and were collected by Margaret Grierson from her professional and personal association with Mary Beard.
Libraries--Special collections--Women--History--Sources; Women historians--United States; Women--Historiography; Women--History--Sources; Women--Japan--History--Sources; Women's rights--Japan--History--Sources; Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948; Brush, Dorothy Hamilton--Correspondence; Grierson, Margaret Storrs--Correspondence; Hansl, Eva B. (Eva vom Bauer) --Correspondence; Kato, Shizue, 1897-; correspondence; articles; Manuscripts; photographs; clippings; Books; Beard, Mary Ritter, 1876-1958; Grierson, Margaret--Correspondence; Sophia Smith Collection--History; World Center for Women's Archives, Inc. (New York, N.Y.); Vagts, Detlev F.; Beard, Mary Ritter; Beard, Arlene; Cott, Nancy F.; Turoff, Barbara
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Biographical clippings, 1933; 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter re: Charles's death, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1946; 1954; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Outgoing
    - Brush, Dorothy, 1946-56; undated (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Chamberlain, Katharine Beecher Stetson, (daughter of Charlotte Perkins Gilman), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hansl, Eva, (includes typescript of American Heritage Women's Activities with suggestions by Beard), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lachmund, Alice, 1942-50 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Leland, Marine, 1947-51 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Grierson, Margaret, (includes letters to Grierson and Marine Leland), 1941-56; undated (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
    - Sanger, Margaret, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Weed, Ethel, 1946-51 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Microfilm: The Letters of Mary R. Beard, 1934-1955. Microfilmed from the holdings of the Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College (housed in microfilm collection), 1934-55 (Box M39)
      General
      [see Appendix for complete list]
  - Incoming
    - Belgum, Florence Richter, (includes biographical sketch of Emelie Richter and Niebohrn[?]), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bromer, Annie, re: Speaking of Women, an international magazine for peace, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Kato, Shidzue, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lachmund, Alice, 1939-42 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - May, Edith Hooper, re: Speaking of Women, includes speech and magazine foreword, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Wagner, Elin, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Weed, Ethel (includes notes re: Shidzue Kato and women in Japan), 1946-52 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - Published magazine articles, 1930-50 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "A Study of the Encyclopedia Britannica in Relation to Its Treatment of Women": research material and report, 1942; undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Speeches: transcripts, notes, and advertisement, 1933-37; 1947; 1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "What Colleges Teach Young Men or Women": submitted magazine article and correspondence, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Women in Long History: typescript, cir, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Changing Political Economy as It Affects Women": syllabus and bibliography for the American Association of University Women, (includes typescript and publication), 1934 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Women as Force in History: publicity, cir, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - American women's history typed notes [from Dictionary of American Biography?], 1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Notes and research material, (includes "Proposal for the Organization of a Women's Reseach Institute), 1936; 1948-49; undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Women in Long Japanese History/Force of Women in Japanese History
    - Correspondence, third party re: Japan material
      - Grierson, Margaret to Dorothy Brush, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Rilma, "Robbie" to Florence Rose, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Weed, Ethel to Dorothy Brush, 1946; 1950 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Notes by Beard and Dorothy Brush, foreword and chapter, circa, 1940s; 1953 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Research material
      - General: Japanese (English language) newsletters re: Japanese women's history, 1922; Supreme Commander of the Allied Powers Public Opinion Surveys and Publication Analysis, 1948-49; "Japan through Women" pamphlet, 1951; undated documents re: religious history and Chinese women's movement (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Re: Shidzue Kato: history of birth control movement by Kato?, 1947; clippings, 1925, 1946-52; photographs, 1947, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Books (on shelf)
    - America in Midpassage, vol. 1, with Charles A. Beard, 1939
    - American Spirit: A Study of the Idea of Civilization in the United States, Vol. IV The Rise of American Civilization, 1942 (inscribed to Margaret Grierson by Mary and Charles Beard)
    - America through Women's Eyes [editor], 1933
    - The Beards' Basic History of the United States, with Charles A. Beard, 1944, (inscribed to Margaret Grierson by Mary and Charles Beard)
    - The Force of Women in Japanese History, 2 copies, 1953, (one copy inscribed to Grierson, one copy inscribed to Marine Leland)
    - Laughing Their Way, with Martha Bensley Bruere, 1934
    - On Understanding Women, New York, 1931
    - A Short History of the American Labor Movement, 1920
    - Woman as Force in History, 1946 (inscribed to Grierson)
    - Woman's Work in Municipalities, 1915
- SERIES IV. WORLD CENTER FOR WOMEN'S ARCHIVES
  - Correspondence
    - Letters to general membership, (includes list of where some material was ultimately deposited), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Between Beard and donors, (includes third party correspondence), 1938-47 (correspondents include Alice Henry, Kate Baker, Wilhelmina Carlstedt, Katherine Gillette Blyley, Charlotte Dobbin, Lillian Cox Athey, Nellie Sashman [?], Jennie Flood Kreger, Dorothy Boulding Ferebee, and Nettie Palmer) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - General: clippings, list of materials, and notes (author unknown), 1935; 1940; undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Dora Ettinger: report "Political Thought and Action of German Women in the Modern Age," letters to Beard, and notes from Beard, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - "Womanpower in this Election," clipping, Mary and Charles Beard, 1944 (Map-case Flat file)